What? The fucking rudder of purple wing?
何が「紫翼の舵」だ
Do you flatter yourselves to be birds?
鳥にでもなったつもりかよ
Both you and me
俺もお前らも
is still a mole crawling underground!
未だに地下這い回ってるモグラじゃねえか
If you wanna leave the moles, come on seriously!
モグラ抜けたいなら本気で来いよ
I'll take on you even with bare hands!
オレは素手でもかまわない
αὔρα
アウラ
What's the hell that aura is, feeling so bad.
なんだよ　その気色悪い念紋…
Those who can do nothing without relying on somebody else,
誰かにくっついてねえと動けない奴は
go pray quietly and play the boating games!
おとなしくお祈りして　船遊びでもしてることだ！
Let's go back.
さ　戻ろうぜ
Yeah.
そうだな
Shit.
くそっ
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina was the soul of the mud whale.
泥クジラの魂であるファレナ
However that soul was not protecting us at all.
その魂は私たちを守るものではなく
Instead, it took the lives of Shirushi and ate them.
「印」の命を喰らい　奪う存在だった
sentikinesis
サイミア
Those who with thymia, and those who without.
情念動を持つ者と　持たぬ者と
It seems that
泥クジラは
the mud whale was divided into two parts.
二つに折れてしまった　かのようだった
Suo.
スオウ
Are you going to visit Masoo?
みんなも　マソオさんのお見舞いですか？
We've digged some bamboo shoots.
タケノコ掘ってきた
I wonder if he could get up today...
今日は起きてっかな…
I hope so.
だといいですね
Here you come.
どうぞ
It's just like my parents.
…やっぱり　父さんや母さんのときと同じだ
Their sleep time became longer and longer.
だんだん寝ている時間が長くなって
And they lost their consciousness...
意識がはっきりしなくなって…
Chakuro, are you OK?
チャクロ　大丈夫か？
Huh?
え？
You don't seem well today.
今日　ずっと元気ないだろ
I... I just had a sleepless night...
あ…あまり眠れなかったから…
Masuo?
マソオさん？
You sloth!
このナマケモノが
How long are you going to sleep!
いつまで寝る気だ
I recalled something...
…思い出してたんだ
No, many things...
いろんなことを…
I thought everyday is the same,
来る日も来る日も
we just repeating the same life.
おんなじような生活　繰り返してると思ってたけど
But everyday is different from each other.
一日一日がちがってた
We knew we are the descendants of the sinners, and we fought.
俺たちが罪人の末裔だと知って　戦って…
Why we had to hurt others...
なんで人を傷つけなきゃならなかったのか…
But you are not dirty.
でも　汚れてなんかないからな
I was the only one bloody.
血に塗れた悪いもんは
I will bring all the sins with me into the sea of sand.
俺がぜんぶ砂の海に持ってくから…
So please live confidently, forever...
だから　どこでだって堂々と生きてくれよ
I will bring the pains and the sadness...
辛いことも　悲しいことも　俺が
No, I refuse!
いやです
Even the pains and the sadness is my precious memories.
辛いことも悲しいことも　私には大事なことです
So don't bring them with you.
だから　もっていかないで
Yes, Masuo. The mud whale is going on a new journey.
そうだぞ　マソオ　泥クジラはこれからなんだ
We need you to continue work hard!
まだまだ働いてもらうからな！
I thought so...
…そう言うと思った
Did you make an appointment?
約束はされているのですか？
No, I didn't.
いや　していない
ατσάλι
ατσάλι
You are going to visit Atsali, who is a great commander.
アツァリ長官ほどの要人にお会いするのに
It's better to...
突然とは…
If I made an appointment with him, he might run away from me.
約束していると逃げられるかもしれない
It's better to go surprisingly.
突然行くのがいいのさ
What happened?
どうした？
Whew...
…やれやれ
It seems that I was so disliked.
私はよほど嫌われているらしい
♪　からっぽの靴　からから鳴った
♪　からっぽの靴　からから鳴った
♪　からっぽの帽子　あなぼこだらけ
♪　からっぽの帽子　あなぼこだらけ
♪　空から目玉が降ってくる
♪　空から目玉が降ってくる
♪　からっぽ　からっぽ　なんにもない…
♪　からっぽ　からっぽ　なんにもない…
Dodge it! You were able to do so, right?
よけろよ　よけられただろ？
The driver died, I ask your help.
御者が死んだ　代わりを頼む
ατσάλι
ατσάλι
These guy are sent by Atsali, right?
こいつら　アツァリのとこの奴らだろ？
Yeah, but he is not that serious.
ああ　だが本気じゃないな
It should be a warning only.
警告というところだろう
όρκα
όρκα
Orca-sama~
オルカさまぁ
I hurt your beautiful hair.
美しい御髪を
Sorry for my miss.
狙いが外れて　ごめんなさい
What's wrong with you?
お前　どうした？
όρκα
όρκα
Cuz Orca-sama is the only one I can rely on.
だって　オルカさまに頼らないとオレ
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Or I can't get back to Fallaina!
ファレナに戻れないんだもん
I wanna be there now, I wanna kill them one by one carefully!
今すぐ戻って　ひとつずつ　ていねいに壊してあげたい
I wanna mess them up cautiously!
とってもだいじに　めちゃくちゃにしてあげたい…
I wonder... if I was left in that island...
オレ…あの島に　オレを置いてきちゃったのかなあ…
I am empty now, I can't even make a sound.
今のオレ　からっぽでなんにも音がしないんだ
Excuse me, I'm here without an appointment.
約束なく失礼を
Did you become hating me?
私は長官どののお眼鏡にかないましたか？
Who is that guy?
その者は？
She is my record clerk.
私の記録係です
It seems that she has her emotions returned.
随分　感情が戻っているようだが
σάρξ
サルクス
Yeah, I have given her the sárx.
ええ　「魂肉」を与えておりますから
νοῦς
νοῦς
σάρξ
σάρξ
Eating sárx, the meat of Nous vouchsafed by his Majesty according to one's status,
地位に従って皇帝より賜る　ヌースの肉「サルクス」
can avoid one's emotions from being taken by Nous.
それを食すことによって　感情を取られる幅が少なくなり
Therefore one's mind returns.
心が戻ってくる
σάρξ
σάρξ
Only ancestry within the fourth degree of kinship can eat sárx vouchsafed to you.
サルクスが許されるのは　三親等までのはずだ
Of course I know.
もちろん　承知しております
I know it better than commander.
少なくとも長官どのよりは
What?
何？
You and your family
あなたの一族では
σάρξ
σάρξ
have distributed the sárx to many people
多くの方々にサルクスが分け与えられているとか
including your cousins and that person.
いとこやその子にも
We are birds of a feather,
同じ穴のムジナが
καρχαρίας
καρχαρίας
why do you want the Karcharías so badly that you even threaten me to get it?
脅してまでカルハリアスを手に入れたいか
I'm not threatening you.
脅しなんてとんでもない
In my case,
ただ私の場合
I can simply marry her.
彼女と婚姻関係を結べば
Then it's legal. That's what I want to mention here.
罪とはならないことも申し添えておきます
I don't want kill...
ころしたくない…
Please... Please take everything from my mind!
もっと…　もっと心を取ってください
ατσάλι
ατσάλι
Do you want to be hostile to commander Atsali?
アツァリ長官を敵にまわすおつもりですか？
Commander will definitely grant our request.
長官は必ずこちらの要望を呑む
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
δαίμονας
δαίμονας
Then we shall go get Fallaina and the Daímonas boy.
その後はファレナとデモナスの少年を手に入れる
νοῦς
άνθρωπος
άνθρωπος
そして皇帝陛下から第一のヌース　「アンスロポス」を奪う
In order to create a supreme world.
至上の世界を創るために
Are you... joking?
冗談…ですよね？
Rebellion is the most serious crime.
反逆罪はもっとも重い罪です
άνθρωπος
άνθρωπος
And you even want the Anthropos...
ましてや　アンスロポスを…
Yes.
そうだ
I will be killed if my scheme get disclosed.
この陰謀が発覚したら私は殺される
Why... are you telling me something so important?
…なぜ　そんな大事なことを私に言うんです…？
My destiny is in your hand.
私の運命は君が握っている
That is what the wife do.
妻とはそういうものだろう？
Note: Jakko is the land in which Buddha reside.
廃国の寂光に戻るとき
shall we pick up your soul.
我らがその魂を拾うだろう
Let the hot sand boil!
熱砂よ　たぎれ
Our hearts are burning forever.
こころは永久に燃えるだろう
Let the hot sand run!
熱砂よ　走れ
Our bodies will rise again and again.
からだは幾度も立ち上がり
We will be the eyes and the foots of our warrior.
我らは戦士の目となり　脚となり
Going on a journey together.
共に悠久の旅をゆく
Suo-sama!
スオウさま！
We still want Masuo to eat bamboo shoots.
マソオさんに　もっとタケノコ食べてほしかった
And drink juice.
ジュースも
Put them all into the coffin.
全部　棺に入れましょう
He will be hungry in the journey.
旅に出れば　お腹が空くでしょうから
Don't cry...
泣いちゃだめだ…
I don't!
泣かないぞ…
Don't mind!
…かまわん！
Cry out today!
今日は泣け！
Why don't you cry?
君は泣かないのかい？
Isn't he somebody you know well?
知り合いが死んだんだろ？
Or, you simply can't cry?
それとも　泣けないのかな
If you can't cry, then it's fine not to cry.
泣けなくても仕方ないし　泣かなくてもいい
Don't mind.
気にすることはない
It is better to treat it as something not related to us.
自分には関わりのないことだと　思ってしまった方が
That's what you have done.
あんたはそうやってきたんだな
Perhaps.
さあ
I forgot.
忘れてしまったよ
It's the first time I saw Oni cry.
オウニが泣いてるの　初めて見た
I am...
俺は…
A number of records that left by our ancestors,
祖国を追われた先達が残してきた　数々の記録
The sand poems written by the previous chiefs.
歴代の首長たちの砂詞
This is the history of the prisoners on the sea of sand.
砂上の牢獄に囚われた人たちが　紡いできた歴史…
And it's a sorrowful history of short-lived Shirushi,
短命の「印」と　それを送りつづけた「無印」の
as well as the Muin who kept send them off.
悲しみの歴史
The history of mud whale...
泥クジラの歴史…
An oath for the Shirushi of Muin.
「印」のための「無印」の誓い
That's what we have written, our history.
私たちが紡ぐ　私たちの歴史…
Hey, what's wrong with you?
ねえ　どうしたの？
Why are you so painful?
なぜ　そんなに苦しいの？
Neri?
…ネリ？
I think I know your pain a little.
その痛みなら　私も少しは分かると思うわ
It's even more painful than being stabbed by a sword.
剣で刺されたときより
It's even more painful than having drunk the poison.
毒を飲まされたときより
Isn't it?
ずっと辛いんでしょう？
May I help you cancel that pain?
その痛みを消してあげましょうか？
You will fly from here.
ここから飛ぶの
Fly higher than the star locusts, and go far away!
ホシボシバッタよりも高く　遠くへ！
Then your pain and your misery will go away.
そうすれば　痛みも苦しさも消えてなくなるわ
You will be free!
自由になれるの
What?
ん？
It's fine?
いいの？
I will be here.
私は　ここにいる
Oh? Then I won't help you.
そう　じゃあ　いいわ
It's your own choice.
あなたが選んだことだものね
Grandpa Kogare, look!
コガレじいちゃん　見て
This is the mud whale,
こっちが「泥クジラ」で
and this is star locust!
こっちが「ホシボシバッタ」！
Oh, you have already remembered them.
ほう　チャクロはもうそんなに覚えたのか
What about the next?
次は？
Teach me the next word, Grandpa Kogare!
次の字を教えて　コガレじいちゃん
All right, I will teach you Sunamodori.
それじゃあ　「スナモドリ」を教えてやろう
Hey Chakuro,
ねえ　チャクロ
am I strange?
私って　変？
Huh, why?
え　何が？
Urumi and Aine told me,
…ウルミとアイネに言われたの
I am like a sister to Chakuro.
チャクロといると兄妹みたいだって
Yeah, you are.
うん　そうだね
I am not! I am not your sister!
違うもん！　兄妹じゃないもん！
Uh? But I know it.
え？　うん　知ってるけど
You don't!
知ってない！
Huh?
え？
Huh...
え…？
Ouch!
わあっ
Chakuro, what do you think about me?
チャクロ　私ってどんな子だと思う？
About you? Eh...
どんな？　え〜と…
You don't need to tell me, but write it down!
言わなくてもいいから　ちゃんと書いて
Write?
書く？
Yes!
そう！
Tell everyone clearly what a girl I am.
私がどんな女の子か　みんなが分かるように
So everyone will remember me with your words.
読めば　みんなが思い出してくれるように
That's it... I wanted to tell everyone...
そうか…　俺　みんなに伝えたかったんだ
I wanted everyone to remember...
ずっと覚えていてほしかった…
Sami and Grandpa Kogare, as well as Taisha-sama and Masuo,
サミやコガレじいちゃんや　タイシャ様やマソオさん
the people died before me,
俺の前から去っていった人
the time on the mud whale, the happiness,
泥クジラで過ごした時間　楽しかったこと
the reasons of tears, all of them...
涙のわけ　全部全部
That's why I was writing.
だから…　書いてたんだ…
So this is what you have decided.
それがお前の決めたことか
Yes.
はい
I wonder if Shirushi are able to bear it...
「印」たちは堪えられるかしら
What will you do if they become desperate?
絶望し　自暴自棄になったら　どうする
But we can't just stay in the mud whale, accept their short lives,
泥クジラにとどまり　短命を受け入れ
and refuse the changes and the future!
変化と未来を拒むか
We should choose the new world and possibilities!
それとも　新世界と可能性を選ぶか
For me,
私なら
I don't want to regret when I die.
死を迎える時　後悔はしたくない
A gather for everybody...
全員が集まるって
It's the first time since the enemies' attack.
この間の敵が襲ってきた時以来じゃない？
Don't say there's another...
まさか　また？
I'm scared!
こわいよ〜
What I can do now, is to keep the truth.
今の俺にできるのは　真実を残すこと…！
Suo.
スオウ
It's about to go, are you fine?
そろそろだ　行けるか？
You need consciousness and responsibility as a leader.
人を束ねる者には　自覚と責任が必要だ
You can't lead people without being ready to have them.
覚悟なしでは務まらぬ
Yes.
…はい
I will tell...
伝わってくる…
The anxiety, the fear, and the incredulity...
不安　恐怖　懐疑…
They are...
それは…
our strong desire to live.
生きたいという強い希望…
I want to record the lives of this ship and the people on this ship.
俺は　この船と船の民たちの　命の記録を伝えたい
I am the Chief Suo.
…首長のスオウです
Thank you for your gathering.
よく集まってくれました
Today, as a Muin,
今日「無印」の一人として
I have to tell something to every Shirushi.
「印」の皆さんに
Since I was a child,
私は幼い頃から
I feel sad about Shirushi's short lives,
「印」の皆さんが若くして亡くなっていくことが
your fate of dying young.
悲しくてなりませんでした
Muin can live tens of years,
「無印」は何十年と齢を重ねることができるのに
but why Shirushi can't?
なぜ「印」はそうでないのか
I always think it's unreasonable and not fair.
いつも歯がゆく　理不尽だと思っていました
Oni!
オウニ！
Captain...
…団長か…
Are you looking for him?
彼を探しているのかい？
I can't find him everywhere.
どこにもいないんだ
We are gathering for Suo's speech...
スオウの話を聞きに　みんな集まってるってのに…
The chief's speech, OK.
首長の話を　ね
Huh?
え？
Oni is different from you.
オウニは君たちとは違う
Don't you know?
分かってるかい？
Oni is...
オウニは…
He will never keep company with anybody.
彼は誰とも混ざらない
One day he will leave you.
いつか必ず離れていく
You don't even know Oni well!
オウニのこと何も知らないくせに！
Why can you say...
なんで　そんなこと言う…
It's my advise.
忠告ってヤツだよ
Oni!
オウニ…！
She is our fellow.
こいつは俺たちの仲間だ
I don't cry.
俺は泣かない
But I also don't forget them!
だからといって忘れたりしない！
Then you shall go.
なら　行くといい…
Kicha, let's go.
…キチャ　行くぞ
Ya, yeah.
う　うん…
You don't cry...
…「泣かない」か…
The mud whale is eating our lives?
泥クジラが　俺たちの命を喰らっていたのか？
Then what the Muin are!
じゃあ「無印」は何なんだよ！
My child might have a longer life...
あの子はもっと長生きできたかもしれないってこと？
In other words, Muin are depriving our lives!
つまりは「無印」の奴らが　俺たちの命を奪ってたってことだ！
Those old guys are sacrificing us to keep them on the sea!
老いぼれたちが海に沈まずにすむよう
They are not just drags for us,
足手まといだけなら　まだしも
but they are also robbing us!
あいつらは強盗だ！
No, they are killing us!
いや　人殺しだ！
Stop it!
やめろ！
Suocchi!
スオっち！
What have you done! You coward!
なんてことするんだよ！　この卑怯者！
Are you standing on Muin's side as a Shirushi?
「印」のくせに　「無印」の味方をするってのか？
If we are coward, then you are a traitor!
俺たちが卑怯者なら　お前は裏切り者だ！
A lot of Shirushi died in the previous war.
この間の戦いで大勢の「印」が死んだ
Do you mean they were deceived by the Muin,
それを「無印」にだまされた挙げ句の
and their deaths are wasted?
無駄死にだって言うのか
Those who died...
死んでいった奴ら…
Nibi, Aijiro, Buki,
ニビも　アイジロも　ブキも…
and many others,
他の大勢の奴らも
they fought and died for everybody here in the mud whale!
みんな　泥クジラの全員のために戦って死んでいったんだ
It has nothing to do with Shirushi or Muin.
「印」も「無印」も関係なく
Even they will never know the truth.
たとえ真実は知らなくてもな
I will never forget they were living here!
俺は奴らが生きていたこと　絶対に忘れたりしない！
Please understand.
分かってください
Our ancestors were not keeping silence for their own peace.
先達は自分の安寧のために沈黙を選んだのではないことを
Muin never want you short-lived Shirushi to live with fear and sympathy.
「無印」は「印」に
We want you to enjoy splendid short lives!
短くとも　精一杯生きることを謳歌してほしかったのです
Of course Taisha-sama and Hakuji-sama also wanted.
タイシャ様はもちろん　ハクジ様も…
All the Muin wants that.
「無印」はみなそうです
That is the Cage of Fallaina!
これが「ファレナの檻」か！
We must get out here soon, it's dangerous!
早くここを抜けなきゃ　危ないんじゃないのか！
There are still creatures here!
こんなところにも生き物が…！
Ouch, Ham?
うわっ　ハム？
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Kókkalo!
コカロ！
Ah, wait!
あ　待って！
Neri!
ネリ
Neri, are you looking?
ネリ　見てる？
Ah...
あっ…
Are you OK?
大丈夫…？
Huh? Ah...
え？　あ？
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
Huh?
え？
Why did Lykos apologize?
なんで　リコスが謝るの？
Don't you hate me?
私を憎んでいるんじゃないの？
Of course no!
違うよ！
Eh, I was surprised when I heard your words.
…いや　リコスの話を聞いた時は　びっくりした
I felt uncomfortable.
やりきれない気持ちになった
Sami and Nibi,
サミやニビ
as well as Musuo, I feel sorry for every Shirushi's death.
マソオさんや「印」のみんなが亡くなったことは悲しい
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
But we can't blame Fallaina for all of them.
だけど　それを全部ファレナのせいにするのは
From now on, I will share all the truths with everyone.
これから私は　すべての真実を皆さんと共有します
Now we have the rudder, we can decide where we are going.
舵を得て　船の行く先を決められるようになった今
It's time for us to find new friends.
私たちは新たな仲間を探しに行く時が来たのです
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Together with Fallaina,
ファレナと共に
let's aiming to the new word, the land of freedom!
新たな世界　自由の大地を目指しましょう！
Translator
字 幕 入 力
ssnake
ssnake
♪　私たちを
字 幕 入 力
Please find us
ssnake
♪　見つけておくれ
♪　見つけておくれ
Timing
字 幕 編 集
zwc1991
zwc1991
♪　泥の舟で櫂を漕ぎ
♪　泥の舟で櫂を漕ぎ
♪　白砂の褥で眠る
♪　白砂の褥で眠る
♪　小さな旅人よ
♪　小さな旅人よ
♪　千重の時間の中
♪　千重の時間の中
♪　必ず出会うけれど
♪　必ず出会うけれど
Oni.
オウニ
♪　蝶の落涙のように
♪　蝶の落涙のように
Let's make friends when we arrive at Amonlogia!
アモンロギアに着いたら　ともに仲間を作りましょう
It doesn't matter
どこで生まれたとか
♪　二度と触れられない
♪　二度と触れられない
where you were born, or what power you have,
どんな力を持っているとか　関係ない
if we have strong friendships and deep bonds.
強く深い絆で…
♪　ただひとつになろうとしても
♪　ただひとつになろうとしても
And I want you
そうして　あなたには
to be the leader of our new community.
新しい共同体のリーダーになってほしいんです
I want you to be the pivot of everybody's heart.
みんなの心の要に
If you are not confident, you'd better refuse it as soon as possible.
自信がないなら　早めに断ったほうが無難だな
♪　無限のちらばりにしかなれない
♪　無限のちらばりにしかなれない
we will be apart forever
ロハリト様　はっきりものを言い過ぎです
Oni will surely become popular among us.
オウニならきっと人気者になります
What?
はあ？
What did you say? I can't stand it!
何だと？　それは聞き捨てならん！
It's a pinch for Roharito-sama!
ピンチですよ　ロハリトさま
What?
ん？
♪　私たちを
♪　私たちを
This is our new ship.
これが私たちの新しい船だ
How wonderful it is!
見事なものだろう
♪　見つけておくれ
♪　見つけておくれ
Everywhere is empty.
どこもかしこも　からっぽだあ
We will soon depart!
出立は　まもなくだ
♪　泥の舟で櫂を漕ぎ
♪　泥の舟で櫂を漕ぎ
Rowing the paddles of the mud ship
全ては「帝国のために！」
If you can meet...
…妹さんに
What?
ん？
I hope you can meet your younger sister.
妹さんに会えるといいですね
♪　白砂の褥で眠る
♪　白砂の褥で眠る
♪　小さな旅人よ
♪　小さな旅人よ
Mama, you must felt.
ママ　感じる？
We are going on a journey.
旅立つのね　私たち
I want...
私は…
Eh?
え？
Even I will have to shorten my life,
命を削って生きることになっても
even I will have to abandon my hometown,
故郷を捨てることになっても…
I want to live here, with Chakuro and your fellows.
ここでチャクロたちと一緒にいたいと思った
Yeah.
…うん
We are living in the mud whale, we are the children of the mud whale.
俺たちは泥クジラと生きる　泥クジラの子だ
It is great I was born here.
ここに生まれてよかった
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
It is great I can live with us.
みんなと一緒にいられてよかった
And even in the future...
そして　この先もずっと…
Towards the future, go ahead
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
If you can be our guide
導かれたのなら
The mud whale had crossed the torrent called the cage of Fallaina,
泥クジラは
Thousands of words, leaving for the fantasy lands
幾千の声　空想の地へ
and was heading to Amonlogia.
アモンロギアへと舳先を向けた
Steering towards the opposite
舵を切って行こうとした
It was August 16, 93 S.S.
時は砂刑暦93年
Thousands of songs, they are the ballads of the sea of sand
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌